<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The baronets buriall, or A funerall sermon preached at the solemnitie of that honourable baronet Sr Edvvard Seymours buriall. By Barnaby Potter Bachelor in Divinitie, fellow of Queenes College in Oxford, and preacher to the towne of Tottnes in Devon</title>
            <author>Potter, Barnaby, 1577-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114967</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850188</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09867)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 933:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The baronets buriall, or A funerall sermon preached at the solemnitie of that honourable baronet Sr Edvvard Seymours buriall. By Barnaby Potter Bachelor in Divinitie, fellow of Queenes College in Oxford, and preacher to the towne of Tottnes in Devon</title>
                  <author>Potter, Barnaby, 1577-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Seymour, Edward, --  Sir, 1562 or 3-1613.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15375:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>THE BARONETS BVRIALL,</hi> OR A FVNERALL SERMON PREACHED at the ſolemnitie of that Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Baronet S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> EDVVARD SEYMOVRS buriall.</p>
            <p>BY BARNABY POTTER <hi>Bachelor in Divinitie, Fellow of Queenes Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege in Oxford, and Preacher to the Towne of Tottnes in Devon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 10. 7. </bibl>The memoriall of the iuſt ſhall be bleſſed, but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</q>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by Ioſeph Barnes. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15375:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15375:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> EDVVARD GILES, KNIGHT HIGH Sherife of <hi>Devon;</hi> and to his right ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Religious Lady, the Lady MARY GILES: <hi>B. P.</hi> wiſheth increaſe of all heavenly graces in this life, and in that other, eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, both to them and all theirs.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Knowe there are many that will wonder at me, and thoſe moſt that knowe me beſt, that after no leſſe then tenne yeares labour and toile in the Lords harveſt, I ſhould hope to approue my paines, or improue my praiſe or profit with theſe few ſcattered eares, in ſuch a plentifull crop of all kind of fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bookes that are dayly brought into the Lords barne. To theſe I may profeſſe, and if need were proteſt, that it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my praiſe, nor profit that I aime at; and whatſoever my toile hath beene for theſe ten yeares, yet this little crop was both ſowne, and ripe, and reapt, and brought into the barne, within leſſe then the compaſſe of halfe ten daies, and
<pb facs="tcp:15375:3"/>
therefore I cannot looke either for praiſe or profit for ſuch ſmall paines, Others perhaps will pull me by the eares and put me in mind of that poſition, lately maintained in that great aſſembly of the <note n="a" place="margin">Act at Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford 1613. doctior quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fuit in ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bendo parciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus. Handled the ſame Act.</note> learned, <hi>that the more learned are the moreloath to leaue any thing in print to the view of the world.</hi> To ſuch I anſwer, that it is my loue not my learning that I would ſhew, and therefore I hope the lawiers poſition will ſatisfie ſuch, <hi>amor excuſat in delic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> thoſe actions that proceed from the paſsion of loue are not liable to law, at leaſt pardonable in reaſon. Vnto both theſe obiections I ſay that I had rather the world ſhould condemne me as vniuſt, and the whole Vniverſitie as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, then you ſhould ſo much as thinke mee vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. For ſince you firſt fetcht mee from the boſome of my mother the Vniverſitie, and ever ſince with extraordinary kindneſſe haue harboured me in your houſe, that counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance you haue continually given to my weake miniſtery, that comfort I haue taken from your continually frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the meanes of ſalvation, the preaching of the word, &amp; your willing conformitie vnto it, that extraordinary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which I haue found, not from your ſelues only, but for your ſakes from the moſt and best of the country about you, whether I came as a ſtranger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>may iuſtly chalenge a greater returne of thankfulneſſe, then theſe few indigeſted medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; which as they were firſt preached, and now publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at your earneſt entreatie (whoſe will ſhould bee worth a command to me) ſo muſt I now entreat that they may paſſe vnder both your patronages, whoſe very names, for the loue you haue of all ſides from all ſorts in your country, will quickly procure them a quiet paſſage. If the curious or cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb facs="tcp:15375:3"/>
carpe at them I care not, ſo the faithfull Chriſtian may receaue ſome comfort by them. If your remembrance, with this honourable Baronets (whoſe buriall it is) may liue a little longer by theſe lines, if the day of your death, now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that great pompe and height wherein you haue paſſed the heat of your honourable imployment may bee renewed, and in all theſe my thankfulneſſe testified I haue my deſire. Whatſoever theſe ſhort meditations be, both ihey &amp; their author deſire to be yours, who will not ceaſe when he prayes for himſelfe, to beſeech God for the increaſe of his heavenly graces here, and eternall happineſſe hereafter, both to your ſelues, and all ſuch as are deare vnto you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From your houſe at Bowdon, <date>Aug. 24. 1613.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to be commanded BARNABY POTTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15375:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15375:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>DEVT. 34, VERS. 5.</bibl>
So Moſes the ſervant of the Lord died there in the land of Moab, according to the word of the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a ſeaſon,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Fecleſ. 3. 1.</note> 
               <hi>all things vnder the ſunne;</hi> but of all other things <hi>a word in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 25. 11.</note> 
               <hi>is like apples of gold with pictures of ſilver,</hi> pleaſant and profitable. If any word, me thinks a word of comfort from the mouth of <hi>Gods meſſenger</hi> ſhould alwaies meet with a good ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; eſpecially ſeeing it is a principall part of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, <hi>to appoint vnto them that mourne in Sion, to giue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſay. 61. 3.</note> 
               <hi>vnto them beauty for aſhes, the oyle of ioy for mourning, &amp; the garment of gladneſſe for the ſpirit of heavineſſe.</hi> Yet in this caſe, I finde the ſaying of a ſage <hi>Divine</hi> to bee moſt true, that <hi>it is not ſo hard to giue comfortable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to the ſorrowfull, as to find a fit ſeaſon when to giue it.</hi> For while the ſtreame of ſorrow runnes freſh and full it is vaine and to ſmall purpoſe to oppoſe counſell; paſſions muſt haue leaſure to diſgeſt; <hi>time</hi> doth as much moderate them as <hi>wiſdome</hi> doth. At the firſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is beſt to mourne with ſuch as mourne for the loſſe of friends, and when our teares and theirs are drie to giue counſell. And yet in this caſe I doubt what is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15375:5"/>
beſt; for as before men haue digeſted griefe, <hi>adviſe</hi> comes too <hi>early,</hi> ſo it is too <hi>late</hi> to <hi>adviſe</hi> when they haue <hi>digeſted</hi> it; as before it was <hi>vnſeaſonable,</hi> ſo after it would be <hi>ſuperfluous;</hi> as before it <hi>cannot benefit,</hi> ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it <hi>may hurt</hi> by rubbing a skinned ſore afreſh. This honourable, but heavy and ſad ſolemnitie then muſt beare the blame, if now that ſorrow ſeemes to haue wearied her ſelfe having wept like <hi>David</hi> &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>till ſhe can weep no more,</hi> &amp; with wearines is fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, <note place="margin">1. Sam. 30. 4.</note> I awake (notwithout <hi>true griefe)</hi> the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our great, our <hi>commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loſſe.</hi> When our Saviour was to ſuffer, certaine women well affected, followed him weeping, to whom he ſaid, <hi>weepe not for mee but weepe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 23. 28.</note> 
               <hi>for yourſelues, and for your children.</hi> Let mee with ſome inverſion of our <hi>Saviours words</hi> ſollicite you, which both in <hi>habit</hi> and <hi>heart</hi> beare the greateſt part of this <hi>ſadſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> weepe not for your ſelues, though you haue loſt an honourable <hi>huſband,</hi> a tender hearted <hi>father,</hi> a faithfull <hi>friend,</hi> a kind <hi>maſter,</hi> a mercifull <hi>landlord,</hi> as moſt he hath left behind; but put of theſe privat <hi>paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of ſorrow, and put on the ſorrow of <hi>compaſsion,</hi> &amp; come and bewaile with vs our common loſle: The <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> hath loſt a choice <hi>patrone,</hi> the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth</hi> a chiefe <hi>pillar.</hi> But becauſe this paſſion hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders our attention, &amp; takes vp our heart before hand, and makes men vnfit to heare, as the people of <hi>Iſrael for anguiſh of ſpirit could not harken to Moſes:</hi> therefore <note place="margin">Exod. 6. 9.</note> you ſhall giue me leaue a little, to caſt a vaile over our ſorrow, till wee haue heard what <hi>God</hi> hath to ſay vnto vs by the mouth of me his vnworthy miniſter, from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15375:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
theſe words of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <q>Moſes the ſervant of the Lord died, &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The providence of <hi>God,</hi> (which like a well drawne picture, eies every particular perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this great houſe of the whole world, and is as inward and familiar to every action therein, as our ſpirit is to our raines) did moſt plainely manifeſt itſelfe, in the <hi>birth</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> in the <hi>death</hi> and <hi>buriall</hi> of this <hi>man of God.</hi> For to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his birth and life, wherein both the wiſdome and the power of God were deepely printed, theſe words you ſee call vs to a conſideration of his <hi>death</hi> deſcribed in the fifth verſe: wherein you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſee, wee may obſerue, firſt the <hi>perſon, Moſes,</hi> ſecondly his <hi>praiſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Diviſion</note> 
               <hi>the ſervant of the Lord,</hi> thirdly his <hi>period</hi> and end, <hi>he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> fourthly the <hi>place, in the land of Moab,</hi> and laſtly the <hi>cauſe, according to the word of the Lord.</hi> Had it beene but a privat perſon, yet being ſo rarely qualified as he was who could haue commanded his paſſion ſo much as to bid ſorrow be ſilent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but behold it is <hi>Moſes</hi> a guid, a governour, a prince among the people: or had he bin a governour that had proved either a <hi>traitour</hi> to his <hi>Prince,</hi> or a <hi>tyrant</hi> to his <hi>people,</hi> both Prince and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might haue beene glad, but it is <hi>Moſes the ſervant of the Lord;</hi> or had he beene but gon into the <hi>mount</hi> to talke with <hi>God,</hi> we need not ſo haue grieved, but <hi>hee</hi> is <hi>dead;</hi> or had it beene in his <hi>owne country</hi> the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> (which God had giuen him and his people for inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,) or at home in his <hi>owne houſe;</hi> but it is there in <hi>Mount Nebo</hi> vpon the top of <hi>Piſgah</hi> in the land of <hi>Moab</hi> where he was withinken of that <hi>ſweet country.</hi>



               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15375:6"/>
And yet that you may not be <hi>caſt downe</hi> with all theſe <hi>croſſe accidents,</hi> or cry out vpon <hi>badfortune,</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the <hi>fates,</hi> or father theſe croſſes vpon ſome maligne <hi>aſpect</hi> of the <hi>planets</hi> and <hi>conſtellations;</hi> knowe that nothing hath come to paſſe in all this but by the wiſe guidance and direction of <hi>Gods</hi> alſeeing <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Moſes</hi> a <hi>great</hi> man, <hi>Moſes</hi> a <hi>good</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>dead</hi> &amp; that in a <hi>strange land</hi> but <hi>according to the word of the Lord.</hi> In the words the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>perſon</hi> comes in the <hi>firſt</hi> place to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered; &amp; the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof that <hi>Moſes</hi> a <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> a great <hi>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is <hi>dead</hi> affords vs this doctrine; <hi>that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Doct. 1. A great go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venour quick ly gone.</note> 
               <hi>the moſt carefull &amp; conſcionable Magiſtrates ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not look to liue longer, yea oftentimes dieſooner then other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi> godly <hi>David,</hi> religious <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> are all gathered to their fathers, and the moſt wiſe godly and religious muſt follow them, aſſoone as thoſe perſecutors of his church and children. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For firſt they are but men and therefore mortal. <hi>Gods</hi> in <hi>calling</hi> but men in <hi>condition. I haue ſaid, yee are Gods and you are all the children of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 82. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>moſt high; but you ſhall dy like men, &amp; you princes ſhall fall like others.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the ſinnes of the people doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes provoke God thus to puniſh them by depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them of ſuch benefit which they ſet ſo light of. This puniſhment <hi>God</hi> denounceth by his <hi>Prophet. The Lord God of Iſraell will take away from Ieruſalem and from Iuda hthe ſtay &amp; the ſtrength, even all the ſtay of bread &amp;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">I ſay. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>all the ſtrength of water, the ſtrong man and the man of warre, the iudge, and the Prophet, the prudent &amp; the aged, the captaine of fifty, and the honourable, and the counſeller; and I will appoint children to be their princes, and babes to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15375:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
rule over them; the people ſhalbe oppreſſed one of another, and every one by his neighbour; the children ſhall preſume againſt the ancient, and the vile againſt the honourable.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the Lord doth ſometimes ſuddainely cut the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off that they may not ſee the miſery which hee ſends vpon the church or common wealth; this God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth as a ſpecial bleſſing vnto that good king <hi>Ioſiah; becauſe thine heart did melt &amp; thou hast humbled thy ſelfe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 King 22. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>before the Lord, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou hardeſt what I ſpake againſt this place, and againſt the inhabitants of the ſame, &amp; haſt rent thy clothes and wept before me: behold therefore, I will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thee to thy fathers, and thouſhalt be put in thy graue in peace and thine eies ſhall not ſee all the evill that I will bring vpon this place.</hi> Thus <hi>the righteous periſh and no man conſidereth that they are taken away from the evill to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">I ſay. 57. 1.</note> 
               <hi>come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See then, beloved, what cauſe we haue to <hi>pray</hi> for <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> the life and <hi>perſeruation</hi> of godly <hi>governours</hi> as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> exhorts, to prevent their death to our power: as <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 1.</note> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> praied <hi>David</hi> that he would <hi>not goe forth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 21. 17.</note> 
               <hi>to battle leaſt he ſhould quench the light of Iſrael;</hi> to bee <hi>thankeful</hi> for them when we haue them, and to be <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull</hi> when we ſee them taken away. I know not whether it be our coldneſſe in praying or our careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in praiſing God for ſuch gracious governours as he hath given vs, or whether God be but preparing ſome heavie iudgement againſt this whole land, (his iudgements are ſecret, and I leaue them to himſelfe:) but ſure we are ſenſeleſſe if we cannot ſee how deeply the Lord hath wounded vs in the <hi>head,</hi> and <hi>heart,</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15375:7"/>
whole <hi>body</hi> of this land, the remembrance whereof is yet freſh and bleeding. He hath <hi>wounded</hi> the whole <hi>kingdome</hi> by the vntimely <hi>death</hi> of a moſt worthie Prince, he hath wounded the <hi>court</hi> by the <hi>ſuddaine</hi> cutting off of a moſt wiſe <hi>counſeller,</hi> and now he hath wounded the <hi>country</hi> by depriving it of ſo honorable a <hi>maintainer</hi> of <hi>peace</hi> by righteous iuſtice. If then a <hi>king</hi> thought he had cauſe enough to lament the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a <hi>Prophet,</hi> &amp; not only kindly to <hi>viſite</hi> him but compaſſionately to <hi>weepe</hi> over him; then giue mee leaue as a <hi>Prophet</hi> to bewaile the death of a great <hi>prince,</hi> a wiſe <hi>counſellour,</hi> a worthy <hi>pillar</hi> of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth in the ſame words; <hi>O my father my father the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. King. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>chariots of Iſraell and the horſemen of the ſame; or as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> lamented the death of <hi>Saul: Yee daughters of Iſrael weepe for Saul which cloathed you in ſcarlet, with pleaſures</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 1. 24.</note> 
               <hi>and hanged ornaments of gold vpon your apparell.</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>themſelues</hi> we haue more cauſe to <hi>ioy</hi> and ſaie as <hi>Hierome,</hi> of his ſinnefull time; <hi>Foelix Nepotianus qui haec non videt; Nepotian is a happy man that liues not to ſee the wicked world:</hi> and as <hi>Saint Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh of ſuch a one, <hi>he was not ſo much taken from vs, as from da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi> But for our <hi>ſelues</hi> and ſinnes which haue provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>God,</hi> we cannot <hi>ſorrow</hi> enough. When <hi>God</hi> ſhips his <hi>Noahs,</hi> it is a ſigne there is a <hi>floud</hi> not farre behind; <note place="margin">Gen. 7. 16. 17.</note> when God ſends his Angels to fetch his <hi>Lots</hi> out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> it is a ſigne there is <hi>puniſhment</hi> for that <hi>ſinneful</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen 19. 23. 24</note> 
               <hi>citty</hi> ſhortly to inſue.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>party,</hi> I proceede to the ſecond part his <hi>praiſe, [Moſes the ſervant of the Lord.]</hi> Behold here
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15375:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Moſes funerall ſermon</hi> ſent after him and perſerved for poſterity; And it teacheth vs that <hi>ſanctity is the higheſt honor, and greatest commendations, that can bee given a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sanctitie is the higheſt honour and greateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation that can bee given to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Heb. 11. 24. Eccleſ. 12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>man.</hi> He that refuſed to be called the <hi>ſonne of Pharaohs daughter,</hi> reioiceth here to be called the <hi>ſervant of the Lord. The end of all,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> is this, <hi>feare God and keepe his commandement for this is the whole duty of man.</hi> There is nothing elſe that makes a man to bee a man, without which we are below the brute beaſts. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all titles of countries and kingdomes, <hi>David</hi> had this as the higheſt honor afforded him, that hee was <hi>a man after Gods owne heart.</hi> If the name of a <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 13. 14.</note> ſeeme to imply ſome meaneneſſe and miſery, yet the name <hi>Iehovah</hi> Lord of heaven and earth whoſe ſervants they are, wipes away this blot. How earneſt are we to ſue and ſeek to be in ſome ſervice about the <hi>King?</hi> &amp; there is no ſervice we ſay vnto ſuch. And yet when we haue ſpent our ſelues in great mens ſervice, either they cannot giue vs all they would<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or they will not alwaies giue vs what they can, or if they both would &amp; could they knowe not what is beſt for them to giue or vs to haue: But if wee ſerue God wee are ſure to <hi>lacke nothing that is good.</hi> We may want golde <note place="margin">Pſal 34. 10.</note> and goods, and health and wealth, but then wee may aſſure our ſelues that God ſees theſe are <hi>not good</hi> for vs, elſe he would not keepe them from vs. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever men make difference of <hi>ſervants</hi> and <hi>ſonnes</hi> &amp; <hi>friends;</hi> to <hi>ſeruants</hi> they commend their <hi>buſines,</hi> to our <hi>friends</hi> we commit our <hi>counſell,</hi> but for our <hi>ſonnes</hi> we keepe our choiſeſt <hi>gold,</hi> our choiſeſt <hi>Iewels,</hi> yea the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15375:8"/>
whole <hi>inheritance;</hi> Yet theſe are <hi>all one</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> His <hi>ſervants</hi> are his <hi>friends,</hi> his friends are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his <hi>ſonnes,</hi> and his ſonnes are both his friends and ſervants. It is great favour in <hi>God,</hi> great honor to vs that he wil vouchſafe vs to be his <hi>ſeruants:</hi> but for our ſervice to make vs his <hi>ſonnes</hi> and <hi>friends,</hi> what honor and dignity on earth if caſt in ballance of compariſon herein would not bee found to light? Therfore <hi>David</hi> though <hi>a king</hi> counts this his greateſt credit; <hi>I had rather be a dore keeper in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 84. 10.</note> 
               <hi>the houſe of my God, then to dwell in the tents of vngodly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> For whether we conſider the <hi>worke</hi> or the <hi>wages</hi> both will proue this <hi>ſervice</hi> to ſurpaſſe all earthly things. For what is the <hi>ſervice</hi> of God but <hi>ſanctity?</hi> &amp; what is ſanctitie but the <hi>renuing</hi> of that decaied <hi>image</hi> of <hi>God</hi> according to which we were created, and the <hi>quieting</hi> of our clamorous <hi>conſcience,</hi> which will not be friends with <hi>vs,</hi> vnleſſe we be friends with <hi>God,</hi> and dare not proue ſo <hi>kinde</hi> to <hi>vs,</hi> as proue <hi>falſe</hi> to our <hi>maſter.</hi> Now what <hi>worke</hi> ſo <hi>worthy</hi> vpon earth as to <hi>pray</hi> vnto God, to <hi>praiſe</hi> his name, to <hi>feed</hi> the poore &amp; hungry, to <hi>cloath</hi> the naked, to <hi>comfort</hi> the comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, to do good to al, eſpecially our owne ſoules? &amp; this is ſuch ſervice as we are ſet about, the worſt work that in Gods houſe his baſeſt ſervant ſets his hand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Secondly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>wages</hi> wherewith <hi>God</hi> of <hi>his mercie</hi> not <hi>our merit</hi> crowns our worke makes it much more glorious. <hi>Bleſſings are vpon the head of the righteous but iniquity ſhall cover the mouth of the wicked.</hi> And <hi>ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov 10. 6.</note> ſaith <hi>David, belongeth vnto the Lord and thy bleſsing is vpon thy people.</hi> Salvation which is the greateſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <note place="margin">Pſal. 3 8.</note>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15375:8"/>
is peculiarly appropriated to ſuch as ſerue <hi>God,</hi> as the greateſt prerogatiue <hi>God</hi> can giue; none are bleſſed but ſuch as are ſaved, &amp; none are either bleſſed or ſaved but ſuch as <hi>ſerue</hi> him; and if we reſpect either this life not only while they liue on the earth which is their inheritance, <hi>(the righteous man ſhall inherite the earth and dwell therein for ever,)</hi> but even when they <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 29.</note> are gone their <hi>name</hi> and memory is <hi>bleſſed,</hi> they <hi>grow</hi> in <hi>credit</hi> when the glory of ſinners ſhall <hi>ende</hi> in <hi>ſhame.</hi> Therefore, ſaith <hi>Salomon, the memoriall of the iuſt ſhall be bleſſed, but the name of the wicked ſhall rot;</hi> though <note place="margin">Prov. 10 7.</note> ſinful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are magnified by ſinners, yet they are made abhominable to <hi>Saints: you ſhall leaue your name as a curſe to my choſen, for the Lord God ſhall ſlay yor, and call</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 65. 15.</note> 
               <hi>his ſervants by a new name.</hi> But if they liue never ſo meanely here, yet the glory they ſhall haue hereafter, will recompence all. For if either life, or glory, or a kingdome, or inheritance, will giue content, wee ſhall haue them in abundance. What more deſired among men then <hi>life?</hi> What life more deſired then a <hi>life</hi> of <hi>glory?</hi> What glory compared to the <hi>glory</hi> of a <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</hi> What more glorious kingdome then that that is had by <hi>inheritance?</hi> What inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>gdome like to that which cannot be <hi>ſhaken?</hi> When the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> were little leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proud that <hi>divels</hi> were ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his name whom they ſerued: <hi>true,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, I ſaw Satanfall down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>heaven like lightning; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſse reioice not that ſpirits obey you, but reioice that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk 18. 18, 20</note> 
               <hi>your names are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Reioice not in your eno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled bloods, admired with living praiſes, &amp; preſerved
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15375:9"/>
the iawes of <hi>oblivion</hi> by ſumptuous <hi>ſepulchers,</hi> anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>coates</hi> and armes, large <hi>revenews;</hi> alas it is theleaſt matter of ioy that the <hi>name liues</hi> in bright honour on <hi>earth,</hi> when the <hi>ſoule lies</hi> in the ruſting reſtleſſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of hell: to haue <hi>all</hi> the <hi>kingdomes</hi> in the <hi>earth</hi> to command, and not to haue the loweſt <hi>place</hi> in the kingdome of <hi>heaven;</hi> to quarter our armes with <hi>kings,</hi> and to want the armes of <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> to haue no part in the <hi>red</hi> croſſe of our crucified <hi>Saviour.</hi> Theſe latter only behold as in a <hi>mirror</hi> the glory of the Lord <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 18.</note> with <hi>open face,</hi> and are <hi>changed</hi> by the ſame image fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>glory</hi> to <hi>glory:</hi> from glory here, <hi>for the ſpirit of glory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 14. Pſal. 149. 9.</note> 
               <hi>vpon vs,</hi> vnto glory hereafter, <hi>ſuch honour haue all his ſaints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this then pull downe the pride of all wicked men: be they never ſo high and honourable here in <note place="margin">Vſe. 1.</note> this world, they are worthleſſe and baſe if this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of <hi>Moſes</hi> may not worthely be ſent after them, that they are the <hi>ſervants of the Lord.</hi> For howſoever generous and noble ſpirits, are ready to ſpit at the name of ſlaue and baſeneſſe, yet their ſinfull carriage proues them plainely to be ſuch. <hi>Knowe you not,</hi> ſaith <note place="margin">Rom. 6 16.</note> the <hi>Apoſtle, that to whomeſoever you giue your ſelues as ſervants to obey, his ſervants you are to whom you obey, whether it be of ſinne vnto death, or of obedience vnto righteouſneſſe?</hi> Yea, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtine, Quot vitiorum ſervus tot dominorum, &amp; quot dominorum tot daemonio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: ſo many ſinnes thou ſerveſt, ſo many maſters, and ſo many maſters in this matter, ſo many divels.</hi> For what is it but the powerfull <hi>command</hi> of <hi>ſinne,</hi> which like <note place="margin">Mark 9 22.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15375:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the <hi>divell</hi> in the man poſſeſſed, caſts vs ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>fire,</hi> where we <hi>burne</hi> and boile with <hi>luſt;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into the <hi>water,</hi> where either we <hi>ſwim</hi> in vaine <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights,</hi> or are <hi>drowned</hi> in the drunken <hi>pleaſures</hi> of this flattering world; ſometimes it blowes vs vp into the <hi>aire,</hi> with a giddy deſire to <hi>hunt</hi> and <hi>hauke</hi> after the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> and preferments of the world; and anon againe throwes vs down groueling vpon the <hi>ground,</hi> nayling our <hi>affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> to this <hi>earth</hi> with the covetous deſires of worldly goods? In chooſing a maſter <hi>one</hi> wiſely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſheth vs to beware of three ſorts of men, thy <hi>enimy,</hi> thy <hi>ſervant,</hi> thy <hi>fellow ſervant.</hi> Hee ſerues his greateſt <hi>enimie</hi> that ſerues the <hi>divell,</hi> hee ſerues his <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſervant</hi> that ſerues the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and hee ſerues his <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> that ſerues the <hi>world.</hi> It is <hi>baſe</hi> then to ſerue the <hi>world,</hi> for that is to become a vaſſall to our ſervant: it is an <hi>vncertaine</hi> ſervice to ſerue the <hi>fleſh</hi> ſo way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſo weake, ſo fraile, ſo fickle, that we may feare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very hower to be turned out of dores: it is an <hi>vnthrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> ſervice to ſerue the <hi>divell,</hi> the <hi>more worke</hi> wee doe him, the <hi>worſe wages,</hi> and the more ſtripes, and the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of the leaſt worke we doe him is <hi>death.</hi> It is follie <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23.</note> then to forgoe Gods ſervice, and ſerue any of them, for they <hi>will bring ſhame at the laſt.</hi> Where then is the <hi>glory</hi> of our <hi>gray haires?</hi> where is the <hi>honor</hi> of our <hi>hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>blood?</hi> where the <hi>credit</hi> of our <hi>politicke heads,</hi> when we ſuffer our ſelues to be enſnared with ſin? we know <hi>it</hi> is <hi>evill,</hi> and we know <hi>it</hi> is of the <hi>divell,</hi> and al the world knowes that wee are wiſe enough to know it; we hate the name of it, and we are aſhamed of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15375:10"/>
ſunne when we commit it, we know that the <hi>end</hi> of it is <hi>death,</hi> and the <hi>fruit</hi> of it <hi>ſhame</hi> to our honor &amp; hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and yet we wil not forſake it. Looke but back vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſinnefull liues you that liue ſtill in the ſame; &amp; tel me <hi>what comfort take you now in the</hi> pleaſure of <hi>thoſe ſinnes</hi> which you haue <hi>committed? What profit in thoſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 21.</note> 
               <hi>things whereof you are aſhamed?</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeakes. Nay where is your reaſon &amp; vnderſtanding that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers you not to ſee that by your ſinnes, you are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then beaſts, &amp; in a faire forwardnes to degenerate into divels? I will conclude this vſe with the words of <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> verily, <hi>if the beaſts could ſpeake they would call wicked men beaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond vſe is for <hi>inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that as we deſire that <note place="margin">Vſe, 2.</note> 
               <hi>praiſe</hi> which is <hi>perpetuall,</hi> and that honour which will both hold out here on <hi>earth,</hi> and helpe vs to <hi>heaven,</hi> we will make the <hi>ſervice</hi> of <hi>God</hi> our chiefeſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>care.</hi> Many courſes there are to compaſſe ſeeming honor, but all of them are quickly blaſted and will wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther away. Nay, they are all accurſed and will bring ſhame in the end, but <hi>he that honoureth me him wil I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2 30.</note> ſaith the man of <hi>God</hi> vnto old <hi>Ely.</hi> Diverſe men propoſe divers ends vnto their liues and actions, and therefore vſe divers meanes; One runnes to the <hi>court,</hi> another to the <hi>campe,</hi> a third to the <hi>ſchooles,</hi> all in hope of <hi>honor.</hi> Would you know the ſafeſt courſe in this caſe? Let the honor and <hi>ſervice</hi> of <hi>God</hi> be your chiefe <hi>aime,</hi> ſo ſhall you be ſure, your end cannot be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable. For els what wil you do? Whither will you go to get you a great name? To the <hi>court?</hi> This glorie
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15375:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is like <hi>glaſſe,</hi> bright but brittle, and <hi>courtiers,</hi> ſaith one, <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>are like counters</hi> which ſometime in account goe for a <hi>thouſand pound,</hi> &amp; preſently before the count be caſt, but for <hi>a ſingle penny.</hi> But for true commendations, when all the glory of court &amp; kingdoms ſhalbe daſht, and dampt, and the luſtre of their honor bee wrapt vp in <hi>darknes</hi> or covered in the <hi>duſt,</hi> the memory of our <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall ever be bleſſed; who being in great credit in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> court, and accounted the ſonne of <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ohs</hi> daughter, choſe rather <hi>to indure affliction with the children of God, then enioy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. 25.</note> 
               <hi>eſteeming the rebukes of Chriſt greater riches then the treaſures of Egypt.</hi> Wilt thou ſhew thy <hi>wiſdome</hi> in deepe plots and politique <hi>imployments,</hi> in church or common wealth? Beleeue it, no wiſdome that is not from <hi>heaven</hi> and hath ground out of <hi>Gods word</hi> will hold out long. Whatſoever is repugnant vnto it, or is not ſanctified by it, will end in ſhame: labor rather for a ſanctified <hi>heart</hi> then a politique <hi>head. Achitophel</hi> was as <hi>wiſe</hi> as the moſt, and yet who ever plaid the <hi>foole</hi> ſo <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 23.</note> much as he? The ſhame of his fact like <hi>Naamans</hi> lepro ſic cleaues vnto his <hi>name;</hi> he ſaw his <hi>counſell</hi> contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <note place="margin">2. Sam. 17. 23.</note> and therefore goes home, ſets his houſe in order, and wiſely hangs himſelfe. Yea the <hi>diuell</hi> as deepe a <hi>polititian</hi> as all the men in the world, yet the fooliſheſt creature that ever God made to worke his owne wo. It is not <hi>policie</hi> then that can <hi>praiſe</hi> thee. What is it a <hi>ſweet</hi> &amp; fluent <hi>tongue,</hi> whereby thou canſt tie the <hi>eares</hi> of thoſe that heare thee, and raviſh them with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thy <hi>eloquence? Herod</hi> had <hi>this</hi> &amp; yet hee could <note place="margin">Act. 12. 23.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15375:11"/>
not perſwade the <hi>wormes</hi> to pitty him, nor preſerue his <hi>name</hi> from everlaſting <hi>infamy.</hi> Is it gay &amp; gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>apparel</hi> wil grace thee? No: if every ſilken <hi>coat</hi> had <hi>care</hi> to ſaue his <hi>ſoule,</hi> &amp; all that gliſter with <hi>gold</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out had <hi>grace</hi> within, what a happy world were we in? But all the <hi>pompe</hi> of apparel, in ſilkes and velvets gold and ſilver, cheines and ornaments, wil never haue that honorable commendations, that the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> giues to thoſe poore perſecuted <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which <hi>wandred</hi> vp and downe in ſheepes <hi>skinnes</hi> and in goats <hi>skins,</hi> who notwithſtanding through their faith and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>obtained a good report.</hi> Will you build vp your <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 39.</note> 
               <hi>names</hi> by ſome glorious <hi>buildings?</hi> Looke you lay the <hi>groundworke</hi> in ſanctitie and the true <hi>ſervice of God;</hi> elſe building you may build, but nothing but a <hi>Babel,</hi> a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of <hi>confuſion</hi> which will <hi>fall</hi> downe and cruſh you to peeces. Where is now the praiſe of <hi>Nabuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> pompe? The very rubbiſh &amp; <hi>ruines</hi> of it, are long ſince ruinated, but his <hi>ſhame</hi> for his prowde boaſting, <hi>is not this great Babell, &amp;c,</hi> and his <hi>puniſhment</hi> to feede <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 30, Ibid. 28.</note> 
               <hi>with the beaſts of the field,</hi> ſhall never bee blotted out. Builde vp your ſelues, your ſonnes and families, in the <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and then your houſes and honors ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue longer then thoſe that build them caſtles and cal <hi>their lands and livings after their owne names.</hi> Els feare the curſe which the <hi>Prophet</hi> hath pronounced. <hi>Wo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 11. Jer. 22. 13.</note> 
               <hi>him that buildeth his houſe by vnrighteouſnes, and his chambers without equity, and vſeth his neighbor without wages, and giueth him not for his worke; hee ſaith, I will build me a wide houſe and large chambers, ſo he will make
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15375:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
himſelfe large windowes and ſeeling with cedar, &amp; paint them with vermilion; ſhalt thou raigne becauſe thou clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt thy ſelfe in Cedar? Did not thy father eate and drinke and proſper when he executed iudgement?</hi> Will you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue you name by your numerous <hi>progenie</hi> and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of <hi>children</hi> deſcended from your loines? So might <hi>Ahab</hi> haue hoped, if his ſinnes had not beene a cauſe to cut of his ſeed and poſterity. But we knowe how <hi>his ſeventy ſonnes had all their heads laid in a baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 King. 10. 6, 7 2. King. 9. 33.</note> on one day, his wife <hi>Iezabell</hi> eaten vp with dogs &amp; all his poſterity rooted out as the <hi>Prophet</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. To conclude this point then; let the glory of God, and his <hi>ſervice</hi> be your chiefeſt aime, ſpeake for it, ſtand for it, fight for it, die for it. Sound it in your mouthes, manifeſt it in your liues, defend it with your ſwords, and if need be ſeale it with your blood, and ſo your names ſhalbe bleſſed when your fleſh &amp; bones ſhalbee conſumed, yea both body &amp; ſoule hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py when your names ſhalbe buried in oblivion. The court you ſee cannot truely commend you, your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique heads will no way profit you, your moving e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence cannot better you, your gay clothes cannot grace you, your ſtately houſe litle helpe you, nor your multitude of children maintaine your honour heare on earth, or procure your happyneſſe in heaven: this only title given by the ſpirit of God vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> to be <hi>the ſervant of the Lord</hi> is worth all the reſt and will laſt for ever.</p>
            <p>From the perſon, <hi>Moſes,</hi> and his praiſe, <hi>the ſervant of the Lord,</hi> I proceed to his end or <hi>period, death; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3. Part.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15375:12"/>
               <hi>the ſervant of the Lord died.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">His period, or end. Doct. Neither great nes nor good nes is a good pleate againſt death.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is neither his <hi>greatneſſe</hi> you ſee nor his <hi>goodneſſe</hi> that can purchaſe him a ſuperſedeas againſt the arreſt of <hi>death;</hi> he that had fed many when they were readie to ſtarue for hunger, and refreſhed many when their ſoules fainted within them for want of drinke, hee at whoſe commande came frogges and lice, and haile and darkneſſe and blood and bliſters, hath not his breath in his owne hand. But I haue heretofore ſpent much time in preſſing this point of mans mortalitie, how death without difference of degree or condition ſummons all ſorts of men. Prince and Prieſt, &amp; people the captaine and the common iouldier, the maſter &amp; the man, the miſtreſſe &amp; her maid, haue the ſame end; they may die of diverſe diſeaſes, at diverſe times, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, but they <hi>all die;</hi> death hath the ſole ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of all the worlde, and knockes aſſone at the great mans caſtle, as at the poore mans cottage.</p>
            <p>Would to God we were wiſe to apply this to our <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> owne ſelues: for doth it not iuſtly reproue, ſuch as ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſo much as mind their mortalitie, but liue here as though they thought verily they ſhould never die? If theſe men had no <hi>religion,</hi> yet <hi>reaſon</hi> would teach them, that their ſtrength is not the ſtrength of <hi>ſtone,</hi> &amp; yet this the very drops of water <hi>weareth;</hi> nor our ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of <hi>braſſe</hi> or <hi>iron,</hi> and yet this the ruſt and canker <hi>conſumeth;</hi> but a <hi>vapour,</hi> but a <hi>ſmoake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which the ſunne ſoone drieth, or the wind driveth away. It was wittily ſaid of <hi>Epictetus</hi> the Philoſopher, who going forth one day and ſeeing a woman weeping that had broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15375:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
her <hi>pitcher,</hi> and the next day meeting another woman weeping that had loſt her <hi>ſonne; heri vidi fragilem fran<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi, hodie video mortalem mori: Yeſterday,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I ſaw a brittle thing broken, and to day I ſee a mortall man die.</hi> And what difference betwixt theſe two? Much one manner of way: for take a <hi>glaſſe,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtine,</hi> (which as it is bright ſo is it much more brittle then an earthen pitcher) keepe it fafe in a cupboord, where it may be free from the violence of outward wrong, and it may continue many thouſand yeares: but take a <hi>man</hi> of the moſt pure complexion, of the ſtrongeſt conſtitution, and keepe him as ſafe as thou canſt, hee hath that in his boſome, and within his owne bones that will bring him to his <hi>end. Nay, I heare ſome ſay</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Father,</hi> as I remember) <hi>that ſuch a one hath the plague or the pluriſie, and therefore ſure he will dy, but we may rather ſay ſuch a one liueth, and therefore ſure he will die;</hi> for diverſe haue had thoſe diſeaſes, &amp; did not die of them, but never any man lived that did not die. The conſumption of the liver is a meſſenger of death, the conſumption of the lungs the miniſter of death, the conſumption of the marrow is the very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of death, and yet many haue had theſe diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and not died of them: but there is another kinde of conſumption which could never yet be cured. It is the conſumption of the daies, the common <hi>diſeaſe</hi> of all <hi>mankind,</hi> and whereof all muſt die: <hi>David</hi> ſpake of it, <hi>my daies are conſumed like ſmoake.</hi> Let mee then warne <note place="margin">Pſal. 102. 3.</note> you, and ſtirre vp your meditations of your mortaſity with the words of our <hi>Moſes,</hi> who hath walked that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15375:13"/>
way before vs, <hi>Deut. 32. 29. O that men were wiſe then would they vnderſtand this, then would they conſider their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deu. 32. 29.</note> 
               <hi>latter end.</hi> Wee are <hi>vnwiſe</hi> that wee conſider not the times <hi>paſt,</hi> the evill we haue committed, the good we haue omitted, the benefits of <hi>God</hi> we haue abuſed, the time we haue miſpent; and yet we <hi>grieue</hi> not, becauſe we thinke not yet whether we ſhall die. <hi>More vnwiſe</hi> are we not to conſider things <hi>preſent,</hi> as the ſhortnes of life, the difficultie of ſalvation, the ſmall number of ſuch as ſhall be ſaved; and yet wee <hi>ſhame</hi> not, becauſe we thinke we ſhal not yet die. But <hi>moſt vnwiſe</hi> that we conſider not things <hi>to come,</hi> death, iudgement, hell, al to come; and yet we <hi>feare</hi> not, becauſe (I feare) wee thinke we ſhall never die. <hi>O that we were wiſe, then would we conſider our latter end.</hi> Wiſe <hi>Princes</hi> vſe to prepare tenne yeares before hand for a field of one day; belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, let vs lay vp ſomething every day for the <hi>laſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> When we ſhall wraſtle with death, if wee winne that skirmiſh we haue enough, and when or where wee ſhall come to the conflict who can tell? For <hi>Moſes</hi> when hee was now ready to ſet foot in the <hi>promiſed</hi> land, liues not to enioy it, but when he comes within kenne of it, it pleaſeth <hi>God</hi> to prevent him by <hi>death,</hi> &amp; to take him away in the land of <hi>Moab.</hi> Which is the fourth particular that I propoſed to be handled, name ly the <hi>place</hi> where <hi>Moſes</hi> died.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the land of Moab.]</hi> See after all the care &amp; paines that <hi>Moſes</hi> hath taken with this people, to bring them <note place="margin">4, Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. The place</note> to the <hi>promiſed</hi> land, now that he was come neere the confines and borders of it, &amp; <hi>God</hi> had ſet him in ſuch
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15375:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a place where he might ſee it, hee ſuddenly here calls him out of this life. Whence wee might well obſerue the <hi>fickle ſtate</hi> and condition of all <hi>worldly</hi> things. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> greateſt comfort, I imagine, both againſt the tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the <hi>way,</hi> and weiwardneſſe of this <hi>people,</hi> and the perplexities of his owne <hi>ſoule,</hi> was to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how happy he ſhould bee, when after all this hee ſhould come to liue quietly in the land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> and now behold that he is ready to come into it, he is ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly <note place="margin">Doct. All worldly hopes quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vaniſh.</note> cut of. O the vncertainty of theſe worldly things, O the vanitie of thoſe men that vex themſelues with hope of ſuch things as they ſhall never haue! Great mens favours, and old mens ſhooes, thou maiſt <hi>looke</hi> for, perhaps <hi>hope</hi> for, but never <hi>truſt</hi> to. And yet how many <hi>Cameleons</hi> are there that liue onely by the aire and breath of <hi>hope</hi> (not of heavenly, but) of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, which when a man ſhould put forth his hand to lay hold vpon, <hi>vaniſheth</hi> away and is ſeen no more? One <hi>hopes</hi> to growe rich, &amp; ſuddenly his trade failes him; another <hi>hopes</hi> for his fathers, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther old mans living, and the old man outliues him; a third <hi>hopes</hi> to riſe to honour, and his meanes are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him. <hi>The hope that is deferred,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 12.</note> 
               <hi>maketh the heart ſicke;</hi> If then the hope be <hi>defeated,</hi> mee thinks it ſhould <hi>die. Moſes</hi> had as much reaſon to hope to come to this <hi>happy</hi> land, as any man living of any earthly thing: and yet how is his <hi>hope</hi> quite <hi>daſht,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would not haue dreamed how his <hi>comfort</hi> could haue beene croſt? It is wiſdome then to hope for ſuch things as we may haue, and to ground our hope vpon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15375:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſuch a foundation as cannot faile. Let the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> be the <hi>ground</hi> of thy Chriſtian <hi>perſwaſion,</hi> and ſo thou maiſt boldly hope for <hi>heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond point which from the conſideration of the place I will propoſe and lightly paſſe by, is the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie</hi> of the <hi>place</hi> where wee ſhall <hi>die.</hi> As death ſpares not any <hi>perſons,</hi> ſo it reſpects not any <hi>place.</hi> When thou art <hi>walking</hi> peaceably with thy brother in the fieldes thou maiſt bee murthered as <hi>Cain</hi> was; <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 8.</note> when thou art ſitting quietly in thy chaire, thou maiſt fall backward and breake thy necke, as old <hi>Eli</hi> did: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art at thy devotions in the <hi>Temple,</hi> thou maiſt <note place="margin">1. Sam. 4. 18.</note> dy there as <hi>Zenacherib</hi> did: yea at the very <hi>altar,</hi> as <hi>Ioab:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſay, 37. 37. 1. King. 2. 34. Iob 1. 19. 2. King. 2. 24.</note> while <hi>Iobs</hi> ſonnes were feaſting, the houſe falls vpon them; while the ſcoffing boyes are mocking, <hi>beares</hi> come from the wilderneſſe and devoure them; while <hi>Chore</hi> and his company are contending, the earth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens <note place="margin">Num. 16. 31.</note> and ſwallows them: while the captaines &amp; their fifties are fetching the <hi>Prophet</hi> perforce to the <hi>King,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. King. 1. 10.</note> 
               <hi>fire</hi> falls from heauen and conſumes them. Thus death dogges vs whereſoever wee goe, and hath his darts ready whereſoever we are.</p>
            <p>Let this then teach vs to take heed that wee bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> prepared for death, ſeeing it is ſo vncertaine where it will meet vs. <hi>Go to now, you that ſay to day or to morrow, we will goe into ſuch a city, and continue there a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jam. 4. 13. 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>yeare, and buy and ſell and get gaine, and yet cannot tell what ſhall be to morrow; for what is your life? it is even a vapour that appeareth for a little time, and afterward va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth away; for that you ought to ſay if the Lord will, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15375:14"/>
if we liue, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will doe this or that.</hi> Nay go to you, that by play &amp; <hi>paſtime,</hi> driue away the remembrance of <hi>death,</hi> nay by <hi>ſurfeiting</hi> and drunkenneſſe, <hi>haſten</hi> your owne death, and yet never thinke of dying. How will you dare to looke death in the <hi>face,</hi> whom you would not vouchſafe the leaſt roome in your <hi>hearts,</hi> nay whom eftſoones you did in your daring humours ſcorne &amp; defie? Let <hi>experience</hi> tell whether many do not meet with <hi>death</hi> in places of greateſt <hi>mirth,</hi> now merry and preſently mourned for: whether <hi>a bone</hi> in our meate may not choak vs, or a <hi>haire</hi> in our milk ſtrangle vs, or a ſtone in a <hi>raiſin</hi> ſtop our breath, as it did <hi>Anacreo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs wherſoever we are, whitherſoever we walk, make the meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our end, our <hi>vade mecum</hi> &amp; beſt companion! leaſt, like vnthrifty ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in great mens houſes, having their allowance of <hi>light</hi> &amp; miſpending the ſame in dicing or dancing, or drunkenneſſe; at laſt are faine or rather forced to goe to bed <hi>darkling;</hi> ſo while we neglect the time of <hi>light</hi> in this <hi>life</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath granted, the <hi>night</hi> of our <hi>death</hi> do ſuddainely ſurprize vs when we do litle dreame of it. To him that is to walke through ſome darke and dangerous place, <hi>one</hi> light carried <hi>before,</hi> will do more good then <hi>many</hi> that are brought <hi>behinde:</hi> ſo the ſerious preparation for death before it come, armes vs both with more <hi>confidence</hi> againſt it and <hi>comfort</hi> in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then that which comes not till death call. I will conclude this point with our <hi>Saviours</hi> words; <hi>Take heed to your ſelues leaſt at any time your hearts be oppreſſed with ſurfetting &amp; dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 21 34. 35 26.</note> 
               <hi>and cares of this life and leaſt that day come vpon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15375:15"/>
you at vnawares, for as a ſnare ſhall it come on all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dwell vpon the face of the earth; watch therefore and pray continually that you may be accounted worthy to eſcape all theſe things that ſhall come to paſse, and that you may ſtand before the ſonne of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Giue me leaue now, I beſeech you, to apply theſe things to our preſent occaſion before I proceede to the laſt particular in my text.</p>
            <p>When our <hi>Saviour, Luk. 4. 20.</hi> light vpon a place of <note place="margin">Luk 4 20.</note> the prophet <hi>Iſaias,</hi> &amp; had red it in the audience of the people, <hi>hee cloſed the booke, &amp; gaue it againe to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and ſate downe &amp; ſaid; this day is this ſcripture ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in your eares, and all bare him witneſſe.</hi> I doubt not, beloved, but you wil all witnes with me this daie, that what you haue <hi>hard,</hi> the ſame you haue <hi>ſeene,</hi> and the words which I haue handled, are fulfilled in your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. <hi>Moſes</hi> a <hi>great</hi> man, and our <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>ſervant</hi> of the Lord, is <hi>dead,</hi> and hee died in the land of <hi>Moab</hi> from his owne houſe and home, but it is according to the <hi>word</hi> and the will of the <hi>Lord.</hi> That he is dead, I wiſh, (if it had bin the will of the <hi>ſupremest,)</hi> that we had cauſe to doubt. That he was a <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> lend me but your patience a little lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and you ſhall heare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> is as much as <hi>drawne out, Ex. 2. 10.</hi> And might <note place="margin">Moſes in name.</note> not he ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 18. 16. <hi>He hath ſent downe from aboue and ſaved me, he hath drawne me out of many waters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes pittied,</hi> the diſtreſſed and oppreſſed eſtate of his poore country in their miſery: and when he could <note place="margin">In nature 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> His pitty.</note>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15375:15"/>
do no more, he looked vpon them, no doubt, with a heavy countenance and a ſorrowfull heart, yea with hazard of his owne life hee was ready to redreſſe their wrong, <hi>Exod. 2. 11. 12.</hi> And was not <hi>our Moſes</hi> the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man that would ſtep forth and ſtand vp to <hi>free</hi> his <hi>country</hi> from all ſuch <hi>taxes</hi> &amp; toules, as cunning <hi>catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poles</hi> &amp; prouling officers could haue been content to haue impoſed vpon the people? And when they were ſuch as could not be <hi>helped,</hi> yet I know he did heartily <hi>grieue</hi> at them, &amp; heavily looke vpon them that were oppreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was a man of <hi>peace,</hi> not a peace <hi>keeper</hi> only <note place="margin">2 His peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making.</note> but a peace-<hi>maker.</hi> When he ſaw two <hi>Hebrewes</hi> ſtriue togither, he ſaid, <hi>Sirs, you are brethren, why do you wrong one another? Act. 7. 26.</hi> And who knows not what <hi>care</hi> he had, what <hi>comfort</hi> he took, what <hi>paines</hi> he indured, to compoſe <hi>controverſies,</hi> to prevent law <hi>ſuits,</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <hi>peace,</hi> to procure <hi>loue</hi> among neighbours?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was content to leaue the <hi>court,</hi> where hee might haue lived in great credit and account, and to <note place="margin">3. His pietie.</note> imploy his paines for the good of his <hi>country, Heb. 11. 24. 25.</hi> And who knowes not that it was neither want of wit, or wiſdome to commende him, nor want of friends to countenance him, nor want of meanes to mainetaine him, that kept <hi>our Moſes</hi> from the <hi>court;</hi> but a godly deſire to do his <hi>country good,</hi> wherein nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his purſe nor his paines were at any time wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting? for did he not many times as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, <hi>Exo. 18. 14 Sit from morning till even to heare the matters of the people</hi> 
               <note place="margin">4. His paines.</note> 
               <hi>and to iudge amongst them?</hi> Till of late either his owne
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15375:16"/>
experience taught him, or his friends adviſed him, as <hi>Iethro</hi> did <hi>Moſes. Thou wearieſt thy ſelfe greatly and the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ex. 18. 18, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>people with thee, for the thing is too heavy for thee, thou art not able to do it thy ſelfe alone; prepare thee helpers and let them iudge the people at all ſeaſons, but every great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter let them bring vnto thee and let them iudge all ſmall cauſes; ſo ſhall it be eaſier for thee, when they ſhall beare the burden with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the executing of which works of iuſtice howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <note place="margin">His iuſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</note> 
               <hi>feare,</hi> or <hi>favor,</hi> or <hi>gaine</hi> makes many <hi>faile,</hi> or <hi>faint,</hi> or deale <hi>vnfaithfully:</hi> yet <hi>ſurely,</hi> ſaith <hi>God, my ſervant Moſes is not ſo, who is faithfull in all my houſe, Num. 12. 7.</hi> And who ever could ſay of <hi>our Moſes</hi> that in matters of <hi>iuſtice,</hi> or ſuch cauſes as concerned the good of the common wealth, either <hi>feare</hi> of great men, or <hi>favour</hi> of friends could ſtoppe his mouth, or <hi>bribes</hi> blinde his eies, or his owne private <hi>paſſion</hi> or <hi>profit</hi> prevaile ſo far, as to moue him to ſpeake or do any thing, againſt the knowne truth of the cauſe? but as he was ſingular in <hi>ſearching</hi> out of the truth, ſo was he ſincere in <hi>iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> I know not whether ever hee did ſee that <hi>table</hi> of <hi>Ptolome Arſacides</hi> which the <hi>Emperour Marcus Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> found at <hi>Thebes,</hi> &amp; was by the ſame <hi>Marcus</hi> left as a ſingular treaſure to his ſonne <hi>Commodus;</hi> but ſure me thought I could plainely in his life &amp; cariage of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the courſe of iuſtice, read the ſumme and <hi>ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> which were written in that <hi>table,</hi> which were theſe: <hi>I never preferred the prowde man though he were rich, nor hindred the poore if he were iuſt: I never denied iuſtice to the poore for his poverty, nor pardoned the rich becauſe hee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15375:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
was wealthy: I never gaue reward for affection, nor puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon paſſion: I never ſuffered evill to ſcape vnpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor goodneſſe to go vnrewarded: I never committed the execution of manifeſt iuſtice to another, neither deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that which was difficult by my ſelfe: I never denied iuſtice to him that deſired it, nor mercy to him that deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it: I neuer opened my gate to the flatterer, nor my eare to the backbiter: I alwaies ſought to be loued of the good, &amp; feared of the wicked: Laſtly, I alwaies fauored the poore that was able to do little, and God who was able to do much al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies fauoured me.</hi> This was his faithfulnes in <hi>publique.</hi> Neither did it in his <hi>priuate</hi> carriage leſſe appeare. For <note place="margin">In Private.</note> which of his <hi>neighbours</hi> hath he cauſeleſly vexed? nay whom did he ever vexe? which of his <hi>tenants</hi> hath he cruelly oppreſſed? which of his creditors hath he craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily defeated? whom that ever dealt with him hath he deceived? Surely in this faithleſſe age <hi>cum annulis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Senee.</note> 
               <hi>magis creditur quam animis,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeakes, wherein a mans hand or <hi>ſignet</hi> is better to be truſted, then his faith and <hi>ſoule,</hi> he was not fit to liue. He truſted everie one, and every one (ſhall I ſay) deceived him? no, not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one. He had thoſe with whom he might, with whom he durſt haue truſted his own ſoule, who may now ſit downe, and ſorrow as <hi>David</hi> did, for the death of his deare <hi>Ionathan, 2. Sam. 1, 26. Wo is me for thee my brother Ionathan: very kinde haſt thou beene vnto me, thy loue to mee was wonderfull, paſſing the loue of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſingular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> hath <note place="margin">6. His meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> given to <hi>Moſes, Num. 12. 3 Moſes was a very meeke ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15375:17"/>
aboue all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were vpon the earth.</hi> And ſurely ſuch as heard the <hi>conference,</hi> or heeded the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>talke,</hi> or <note place="margin">In his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> obſerved the <hi>carriage</hi> of our noble <hi>Moſes,</hi> knowe that not many men wil be found more meek then he. In <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> who hath ever hard him clamorous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious? or ſeeking as ſome do rather the <hi>victory</hi> and laſt word, then the truth and <hi>verity?</hi> yea hee would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meekely yeeld, then multiply words ſo that with whomſoever he did confer, his mildnes made it ſweet or profitable. For <hi>where two meeke men meete togither, their conference,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Bernard, is ſweete and profitable: where one man is meeke, it is profitable; where neither, it proues pernicious.</hi> And therfore it was <hi>S. Bernards</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, (and our <hi>Moſes</hi> had learned it,) becauſe he would be ſure to retaine this modeſty, on the one ſide, to be very vrgent vpon thoſe that in their meeknes woulde yeeld much, and to yeeld another time to him that vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. And as his graver conference, ſo his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon <hi>talke</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon talke.</note> did taſte and relliſh much more of <hi>meekeneſſe.</hi> I haue often been vouchſafed his company, yet I never hard him ſpeake <hi>evill</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> or <hi>good</hi> of <hi>himſelfe.</hi> But his <hi>carriage</hi> was the map of meeknes. For beſides his low ly <note place="margin">In his cariage</note> and loving carriage even to the pooreſt, would hee not quietly rather <hi>indure</hi> two wrongs; then <hi>complaine</hi> of one? rather <hi>ſuffer</hi> many wrongs, then <hi>returne</hi> one? rather <hi>put vp</hi> al wrongs, then <hi>revenge</hi> one? And had he not the happy <hi>reward</hi> of <hi>meekenes</hi> attending him, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſweet <hi>content of minde,</hi> and a quiet paſſage of ſuch croſſes as accompany this life: whereby he did enioy both his reſt and ſleepe more ſoundly, &amp; received his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15375:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
meate and drinke more merrily and thankefully then moſt men do. So in him we might ſee it true: that, that which will breake a <hi>proud</hi> and angry <hi>mans heart,</hi> will not breake an <hi>humble,</hi> and meek mans <hi>ſleepe.</hi> I proceed. <hi>Moſes was learned in al the knowledge of the Aegyptians;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 7. 22.</note> In this indeed <hi>Moſes</hi> did overmatch our <hi>Moſes:</hi> but herein our <hi>Moſes</hi> did overmatch the moſt that I haue knowne, that hauing no greater depth of <hi>learning,</hi> he could in any point both <hi>conceiue</hi> ſo <hi>quickly,</hi> and <hi>obiect</hi> ſo <hi>acutely,</hi> and <hi>ſpeake</hi> ſo <hi>iudiciouſly,</hi> and to purpoſe as he did. Thus you ſee that <hi>Moſes</hi> is <hi>dead; Moſes</hi> for his place of <hi>governement, Moſes</hi> for his <hi>pittie, Moſes</hi> for his <hi>peacemaking, Moſes</hi> for his <hi>pietie, Moſes</hi> for his <hi>pain fulneſſe</hi> in his place of iuſtice, <hi>Moſes</hi> for his <hi>faithfulnes</hi> in publike, &amp; his <hi>true heartednes</hi> to his <hi>private</hi> friends, <hi>Moſes</hi> for his <hi>meekneſſe;</hi> &amp; in what one thing hee came ſhort of <hi>Moſes;</hi> it was not ſo much as moſt of his <hi>ranke</hi> came ſhort of <hi>him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which commends all theſe former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, <note place="margin">7. His zeale.</note> is the praiſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> in this place, <hi>the ſervant of the Lord.</hi> And was not our Moses ſuch? For his ſoundneſſe and ſinceritie in the true <hi>religion</hi> &amp; ſervice of <hi>God,</hi> and perfect hatred of <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, all the country can witneſſe with mee. Who hath been more ready to put in execution thoſe good lawes of our land, againſt our wilfull <hi>Recuſants?</hi> Who was ſo great or deare vnto him that he would winke at, in this caſe which concernes <hi>Gods glory,</hi> and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of <hi>religion?</hi> And though in other matters of iuſtice he was as <hi>mercifull</hi> as any man living, yet in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15375:18"/>
the ſervice of God, and puniſhing of <hi>Idolaters,</hi> his <hi>zeal</hi> hath beene <hi>hot</hi> like <hi>Moſes,</hi> who when hee ſaw the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <note place="margin">Exod. 32. 19.</note> fall to <hi>Idolatrie</hi> dancing about the <hi>calfe;</hi> his wrath waxed hot, and he caſt the <hi>tables</hi> out of his hands and brake them in peeces, and burned the <hi>calfe</hi> in the fire, and ground it to <hi>powder,</hi> and made the people of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> to drinke of it, <hi>Exod. 32. 19.</hi> which godly zeal of this our <hi>Moſes</hi> made him ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay, (&amp; me thinks I ſee with what feeling and <hi>fervencie</hi> he ſpake it, when there was none preſent but my ſelfe alone,) that til we might ſee them hanſomely ſhipt, and the <hi>ſea</hi> betwixt vs &amp; ſuch as haue a <hi>Pope</hi> in their <hi>heart,</hi> neither can wee bee <hi>ſafe,</hi> nor the <hi>ſervice</hi> of <hi>God</hi> pure and <hi>ſincere.</hi> Neither can the <hi>country</hi> only witneſſe, but the King and Councell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme their aſſured perſwaſion of our <hi>Moſes</hi> his zeale: when in thoſe diſaſtrous, and dangerous times of the <hi>powderplot,</hi> they pleaſed to appoint him to that highe &amp; moſt honourable office the <hi>command</hi> of the whole <hi>Country,</hi> though hee had not long before borne the burden of that office. What ſhall I ſay of his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar carriage in the ſervice of God? I haue often ſeene him at publike <hi>Sermons</hi> and <hi>ſervice:</hi> ſometime in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate we hane prayed together, and praiſed God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And ſure his diligent <hi>attention</hi> in the one, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing that a word ſhould paſſe him, and his devout <hi>carriage</hi> in the other, gaue good ſignes of a ſincere heart, not willingly ſinning, but willingly ſorrowing when he had ſinned. What ſhall I ſay more? You ſee now, and cannot but ſay, that he was a <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>the ſervant of the Lord;</hi> yet <hi>Moſes</hi> was a <hi>man,</hi> elſe hee had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15375:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not <hi>died;</hi> and ſubiect to his perſonall ſinnes, his faults, his frailties, which <hi>God</hi> doth puniſh, elſe he had not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the land of <hi>Moab.</hi> For if you would knowe the cauſe why <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt not come into the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> but die in the land of <hi>Moab,</hi> when hee is now within kenne of that pleaſant country: the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> hath expreſſed it, <hi>Deut. 32. 51. Becauſe you haue treſpaſſed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 51. 52.</note> 
               <hi>againſt me among the children of Iſrael in Kadeſh, in the wilderneſſe of Zin; for you ſanctified me not among the children of Iſrael: Thou ſhalt therefore ſee the land before thee, but ſhalt not goe thither.</hi>
            </p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Doct." n="1"/>
            <p>See then, and obſerue hence another point of <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,</hi> which in my paſſage I purpoſely omitted, but The beſt men are ſubiect to their frailties and faults. now comes fitly to be handled, namely; <hi>The beſt men are ſubiect to their frailties and falls.</hi> Even <hi>Moſes</hi> though a rare man, yet cannot bee free from infirmities; yea ſometime fals into ſuch ſinnes, as <hi>God</hi> doth ſeverely puniſh. <hi>In many things,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iames, wee ſinne all,</hi> as <note place="margin">Iam. 3. 2.</note> might be made plaine by particular inſtances in the beſt ſervants of <hi>God.</hi> But I take no comfort to vncover the <hi>nakedneſſe</hi> of worthie <hi>Patriarches</hi> &amp; <hi>Prophets,</hi> who when <hi>God</hi> but for a time did leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to themſeiues, did ſtumble and <hi>fall</hi> and lie along vnder their ſinnes. <hi>Optimus ille qui minimis vrgetur; he is happy,</hi> could the <hi>heathen</hi> ſay, <hi>that hath feweſt faults,</hi> and thoſe the <hi>leaſt;</hi> for there is none ſo happy as to haue <hi>none.</hi> Which as <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> it ſerues for a iuſt reproofe for all ſuch as are ready to condemne their brethren, and caſt of their Chriſtian company and kindneſſe, for ſome one <hi>fault</hi> they finde in him, and never looke to commend thoſe good <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:15375:19"/>
which they might ſee; ſo it ſerues</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
            <p>Secondly, for inſtruction vnto the beſt, willingly to ſubmit themſelues to the word of <hi>God</hi> to godly inſtru ctions, Chriſtian admonitions, and wholſome repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions. For none ſo good but ſomething the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> will find amiſle in them which they cannot <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend</hi> till they <hi>ſee,</hi> nor well ſee till the word of <hi>God</hi> ſhew it vnto them. Will not the beſt garments grow duſtie; if they be not bruſhed? the fineſt lane and linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grow loathſome, if it be not waſhed? the ſweeteſt gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den overgrown with netles or worſe, if it be not wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? and the <hi>beſt</hi> man, <hi>worſe</hi> if he will not bee admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, all ſhould learne hence to run to the mercie <hi>of God,</hi> and lay hold vpon the hornes of that <hi>altar. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſum at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſcriptum eſt,</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> vpon the 51. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> concerning the <hi>adultery</hi> and <hi>murther</hi> of <hi>Dauid;)</hi> It is <hi>committed</hi> by him, &amp; by him committed to <hi>writing,</hi> for our <hi>learning,</hi> that thoſe who yet ſtande <hi>fall</hi> not, and thoſe that fall <hi>lie</hi> not ſtill but may riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Stand not vpon the perfection of thy <hi>purity. Patriarches</hi> haue fallen, <hi>Prophets</hi> haue fallen, <hi>Apoſtles</hi> haue fallen, <hi>ſtarres</hi> haue not beene ſo fixed but they haue fallen, <hi>Angels</hi> not ſo firme but they haue fallen. Truſt not then in the righteouſnes of thy <hi>workes;</hi> for they are but polluted; truſt not in the integrity of thy <hi>nature,</hi> for even it is defiled: but rely vpon the <hi>mercy</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for that only is abſolute, &amp; in the <hi>merits</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for they and they only are alſufficient. And ſay with <hi>David: If thou, Lord, wilt be extreme to marke what is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 130. 3, 4.</note>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15375:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>done amiſſe, O Lord who may abide? but there is mercy with thee that thou mayſt be feared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you haue ſeene both the <hi>party, Moſes,</hi> &amp; his <hi>praiſe, the ſeruant of the Lord,</hi> and his <hi>end, he is dead,</hi> and the <hi>place</hi> where, <hi>in the land of Moab.</hi> And as in their <hi>liues</hi> you haue ſeene how like they were, ſo were they in many particulars like in the manner of their <hi>death.</hi> I will only point at them. Both died in a <hi>ſtrange place,</hi> where they were but within <hi>view,</hi> &amp; were now come to take the <hi>comfort</hi> of that pleaſant country, that <hi>God</hi> had promiſed and provided for their <hi>poſterity.</hi> Both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when they were in outward appearancelike to liue long. For of <hi>Moſes</hi> it is ſaid here, <hi>that his eies were not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut 34. 37.</note> 
               <hi>dim, nor his naturall force abated.</hi> And may we not ſaie ſo of this ſecond <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> &amp; ſight and hearing, &amp; other <hi>ſences,</hi> might eaſily be obſerved to haue beene more ſharpe and <hi>quicke</hi> then many that haue not paſt halfe his yeares? was it not much that a man of his yeares, and of ſo much <hi>imployment</hi> ſhould haue at his dying day neither gray haire nor vnſound tooth? Yea, I may ſay it was little leſſe then a <hi>miracle,</hi> that his <hi>vitall</hi> and naturall <hi>powers</hi> ſhould continue eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntill his dying day in that perfection; when all his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall <hi>parts</hi> as appeared afterwards were ſo ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gely cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, as that if the moſt learned <hi>Phyſitions</hi> had knowne the ſtate of his body as they imagine it hath beene theſe many yeares, they could not haue hoped nor conceived how he ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue ſo long in that health and <hi>strength</hi> as continually he did. His <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> was but <hi>ſhort,</hi> and (ſaving ſome fits) not very ſharpe:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15375:20"/>
his carriage therein (I dare ſpeake it vpon the word of thoſe that were continually with him) very quiet and patient. When the Miniſter of <hi>God</hi> came to him, to fit him with <hi>comfort</hi> and confidence againſt the terrours of <hi>death,</hi> having prepared himſelfe for this purpoſe, he entertained him kindly, hard him attentiuely, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed he received much comfort by him, made a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy confeſſion of his faith with his owne mouth, and intreated his company &amp; comfort againe aſſoone as conveniently he could reſort vnto him. In the meane time how his minde was buſied, we may imagine by that worthy acknowledgement of Gods loue vnto him, when he thanked <hi>God, that in all that time of his ſickneſſe hee had neither a bad thought, nor a bad dreame.</hi> But death is now at his doores, and as he liued quietly and peaceably, ſo he layes him downe like a <hi>lambe:</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver opened his mouth to murmure, nor moved anie part of his body to ſtriue and ſtruggle with death: but with a deepe groane, as from a ſorrowfull &amp; repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſoul, ſends his ſoule into the <hi>hand</hi> of his <hi>Savior,</hi> where now, no doubt, he reſts in ioy.</p>
            <p>There followes now <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>funerall,</hi> which (as appeares in the next <hi>verſe)</hi> was performed as honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably <note place="margin">Ver 6.</note> as ever was hard of, euen by <hi>God</hi> himſelfe; yet ſo <hi>ſecretly,</hi> as his <hi>ſepulcher</hi> could never be ſeene vnto this day. And haue not the godly friends of our honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Moſes,</hi> herein ſhewed their <hi>loue</hi> and care, by as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable a <hi>ſolemnity,</hi> as (I thinke) moſt of our eies haue ſeene? The laſt thing is the mourning &amp; <hi>ſorrow</hi> which followed vpon his death. <hi>The children of Iſrael wept for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 8.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15375:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>him in the plaine of Moab thirty daies,</hi> and haue not we as great cauſe to ſorrow in reſpect of our ſelues? And yet that our ſorrowe may not exceede, knowe that though <hi>Moſes</hi> a great man, and <hi>Moſes</hi> a good man, the <hi>ſervant</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> be <hi>dead,</hi> &amp; in the land of <hi>Moab:</hi> yet nothing hath hapned in all this, but by <hi>Gods</hi> appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>according to the will of the Lord,</hi> which was the laſt point I propoſed out of the words of my text, and which I can onely touch now.</p>
            <p>The point of doctrine which wee may obſerue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <note place="margin">Doct. All croſſes commeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God. Amos, 3. 5.</note> hence is this: <hi>What ſoeuer croſſes and calamities doe befall vs here, they come not by fortune or hap-hazard, but at Gods appointment and his all-ruling providence. Can a bird fall into a ſnare where no fowler is? Amos, 3. 5.</hi> Men that lie vnder Gods puniſhing hand or ſome heauie croſſe, are like a <hi>bird</hi> in a net whereinto we often fall, before we ſee the <hi>fowler;</hi> and being caught, the more we ſtriue &amp; ſtruggle to get out, the more we inta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle our ſelues therein. Now it were a ſtrange thing to ſee nets and ſnares ſet themſelues to catch birds without a fowler; and no leſſe ſtrange it is that croſſes and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities ſhould befall any man at hap-hazard without a guide and governour. Which the <hi>Prophet</hi> plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, <note place="margin">Ibid. v. 6.</note> ver. 6. <hi>Shall there be any evill in the citty and the Lord hath not done it? Who gaue Iacob for a ſpoile and Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſay, 42. 24.</note> 
               <hi>to the robbers? Did not the Lord becauſe we haue ſinned againſt him? Iſa. 42. 24.</hi> Howſoever men may attribute the <hi>plague</hi> of peſtilence, to the infection of the <hi>aire,</hi> or party about vs; the calamity of the <hi>ſword,</hi> to the <hi>malue</hi> of the enimy; the deſolation of <hi>famine</hi> to <hi>fowle wether,
<pb facs="tcp:15375:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15375:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15375:22"/>
conſumptions</hi> vnto want of <hi>exerciſe, feuers</hi> and burning agues to the <hi>malignitie</hi> of ſome diſh of <hi>meate</hi> or draught of <hi>drinke,</hi> (&amp; rightly too, as to the <hi>ſecond cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:)</hi> yet the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> wold haue vs to look to a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hand in all theſe: <hi>for it is God that ſends both peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut 28. 21. 22.</note> 
               <hi>and famine, and the ſword, and conſumptions &amp; fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and burning agues, Deut. 28. 21. 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this then (for this preſent) perſwade vs to <hi>pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> vnder al <hi>croſſes.</hi> Thou haſt loſt thy father or friend or childe by vntimely death as thou doſt imagine, and therefore crieſt out either of want of <hi>care</hi> in their <hi>kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> or want of <hi>skill</hi> in the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> or abſence of <hi>friends,</hi> and ſayeſt as <hi>Mary</hi> did to our <hi>Saviour, if thou hadſt beene here my brother had not beene dead,</hi> or thou <note place="margin">Ioh 11. 32.</note> condemneſt thy hard hap, and conſidereſt not, that it is <hi>Gods hand.</hi> Thus haue the children of <hi>God</hi> begunne their ſerious conſultations in the day of <hi>affliction,</hi> and hereby beckned as it were to themſelues for ſilence, <hi>Dominus eſt, it is the Lord.</hi> When that heavie newes came to old <hi>Elies</hi> eares, which whoſoever ſhould hear his two <hi>eares</hi> ſhould <hi>tingle:</hi> hee impoſeth ſilence to himſelfe, and armes himſelfe with this reſolution, <hi>it is the Lord let him doe what ſeemeth him good.</hi> It is the <hi>Lord,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 3, 18.</note> who hath more right to my <hi>ſoule,</hi> then I haue to my ſelfe, more power over my <hi>body,</hi> then I hane over a thought in my ſoule; and ſhall I not be ſilent when he ſends for one of them, and ſaies they ſhall be ſundred? What other <hi>ſhield</hi> was it wherewith <hi>Iob</hi> repelled all thoſe venemous <hi>darts,</hi> which either in the <hi>death</hi> of his <hi>children,</hi> or <hi>loſſe</hi> of his <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> or the <hi>running</hi> of his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15375:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>ſores,</hi> or the curſed <hi>perſwaſion</hi> of his <hi>wife,</hi> or the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comforts of his <hi>friends,</hi> or the malitious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate <hi>accuſations</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> were caſt vpon him, when in all this nothing came from his mouth, but <hi>thanked be God?</hi> The <hi>divell</hi> made no doubt, I thinke, but he would haue blaſphemed, and his <hi>wife</hi> a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous divell in his boſome perſwaded him to curſe, and his <hi>fleſh</hi> and fraikie no doubt was forward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; but what kept him backe? even this reſolution; <hi>The Lord giueth and the Lord taketh away, even as it</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob. 1. 21.</note> 
               <hi>pleaſeth the Lord ſo come things to paſſe.</hi> I conclude with <hi>Tertullian: Totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>licet ſeculum pereat, dum patientiam lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifaciam; I care not though the whole world periſh ſo I may gaine patience.</hi> But our <hi>Moſes</hi> is not periſhed, his <hi>ſoule</hi> liues in <hi>heaven,</hi> and <hi>himſelfe</hi> liues ſtill on <hi>earth</hi> in that noble <hi>ſlemme,</hi> that hath ſprung from his <hi>ſtocke,</hi> &amp; is now riſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp <hi>in</hi> his <hi>ſtead.</hi> Whom I wil humbly ſollicit in the ſame words that <hi>God</hi> ſpeakes vnto <hi>Ioſhua: Moſes my ſervant is dead, now therefore ariſe.</hi> It is now no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <note place="margin">Ioſhua, 1. 2.</note> time for you to pinne vp your ſelfe within your private walls, no time now to ſleepe vpon the bed of pleaſure and delight. <hi>Ariſe,</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> calls for you to ſtand vp in the roome of your <hi>honourable Father;</hi> the eies of all are caſt vpon you, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their harts wiſhing you would be pleaſed, to ſet before your eies your <hi>fathers</hi> footſteps, and to walke therein. Doubt not of Gods bleſſing vpon you in ſuch courſes: but what <hi>God</hi> ſpeakes to <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in the ſame Chap. v. 5. you may imagine even ſpoken to <hi>you: As I was with Moſes, ſo will I be with thee, I will not leaue thee, neither for ſake</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 5.</note>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15375:23"/>
               <hi>thee, be ſtrong and of a good courage.</hi> And againe, <hi>verſ. 7. Only be thou ſtrong and of a moſt valiant courage.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <note place="margin">V. 7.</note> 
               <hi>ver. 8. Haue I not commanded thee ſaying, be ſtrong</hi> 
               <note place="margin">V. 8.</note> 
               <hi>and of a good courage? feare not nor be diſcouraged, for I the Lord thy God will be with thee whither ſoeuer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou goeſt. Behold</hi> a threefold <hi>exhertation,</hi> let it arme you againſt a threefold <hi>temptation:</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>diuel;</hi> all which are linked in a helliſh conſpiracie, to hinder and diſcourage every one in any good courſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuch as are ſet in high <hi>place,</hi> or are imployed for the <hi>publike</hi> good. Hee had need therefore both of a ſound <hi>head,</hi> and a ſanctified <hi>heart</hi> that ſhould hold out in a high <hi>place.</hi> Wherein conſider, I beſeech you, that <hi>your care</hi> of religious cariage ſhould bee ſo much the greater, as <hi>Gods loue</hi> hath beene the more in raiſing you aboue many in the world. The <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of a <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> man is his <hi>owne,</hi> and his <hi>sinnes</hi> ſeldome hurt any but himſelfe, but the goodneſſe of a <hi>principall</hi> man is the whole <hi>countries,</hi> and his ſinnes infectious vnto many. The common meanes which both the <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and <hi>the diuell,</hi> vſe in this wanton age of the world, is the <hi>contagio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of bad <hi>company,</hi> which you haue cauſe to curſe and avoid, becauſe the <hi>canker</hi> common ly eates into the goodlieſt <hi>flowers</hi> in the garden, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſettles vpon <hi>netles</hi> and ſuch worthleſſe weeds. And ſurely ſuch as our company is, ſuch either wee are, or ſuch we will be ſhortly, or ſuch wee would bee thought to be, or at leaſt the world will iudge vs to be ſuch. Let mee therefore beſeech you even for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> the honour of your <hi>houſe,</hi> the good of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15375:23"/>
your <hi>country,</hi> the comfort of your <hi>friends,</hi> the peace of your owne <hi>conſcience,</hi> and the ſalvation of your owne <hi>ſoule,</hi> take heed of <hi>bad company.</hi> Out of good and <hi>godly</hi> minded men chuſe your <hi>acquaintance,</hi> out of your acquaintance cull out ſome fewe for your <hi>friends,</hi> out of your friends ſome one <hi>familiar,</hi> whom you may truſt with your ſelfe; herein, I doubt not, you ſhall find more ſollid comfort and content, then in varietie of company, which will be bold enough to thruſt in vpon you, then in great multitudes which will be ready enough to <hi>flatter</hi> you. In a word (for you are <hi>wiſe)</hi> vſe thoſe good talents of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>wealth,</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> (which <hi>God</hi> hath given you) ſo, as Gods glory may gaine by them, and you ſhall be ſure not to looſe at the laſt. Nay, you may aſſuredly look to heare both on <hi>earth,</hi> and in <hi>heaven, It is well done good ſervant and faithfull: thou hast beene faithfull in much, I will make thee ruler over more, enter into thy maſters ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
